<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The two twins of birth and death A sermon preached in Christs Church in London, the 5. of September. 1624. By Samson Price, Doctor of Diuinitie, one of his Majesties chapleins in ordinarie. Vpon the occasion of the funeralls of Sir William Byrde Knight. Doctor of the Law, deane of the Arches, and iudge of the Prerogatiue Court of the Archbishop of Canterburie.</title>
            <author>Price, Sampson, 1585 or 6-1630.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1624</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 95 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 26 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10080</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20334</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S115217</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99850436</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99850436</idno>
            <idno type="VID">15638</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10080)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 15638)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1358:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The two twins of birth and death A sermon preached in Christs Church in London, the 5. of September. 1624. By Samson Price, Doctor of Diuinitie, one of his Majesties chapleins in ordinarie. Vpon the occasion of the funeralls of Sir William Byrde Knight. Doctor of the Law, deane of the Arches, and iudge of the Prerogatiue Court of the Archbishop of Canterburie.</title>
                  <author>Price, Sampson, 1585 or 6-1630.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 47, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Edward All-de, for Iohn Hodgets,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1624.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Running title reads: The two twinnes of birth and death.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>[Bird, William, --  Sir, 1561-1624].</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:15638:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15638:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE TWO TWINS OF BIRTH AND <hi>DEATH.</hi> A SERMON PREACHED in
<hi>Chriſts Church</hi> in <hi>London,</hi> the 5. of Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tember. 1624. By SAMSON PRICE, Doctor of Diuinitie, one of his Majeſties Chapleins in Ordinarie. Vpon the occaſion of the Funeralls of Sir WILLIAM BYRDE Knight. Doctor of the Law, Deane of the Arches, and Iudge of the Prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatiue Court of the Archbiſhop of Canterburie.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PHILLIP. 1.21.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>To me to liue in Chriſt, and to dye is gaine.</p>
            </q>
            <figure/>
            <p>AT LONDON: Printed by <hi>Edward All-de,</hi> for <hi>John Hodgets.</hi> 1624.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:15638:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15638:2"/>
            <head>TO MY CHRISTIAN AND LOVING PARISHIO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NERS OF CHRISTS CHVRCH IN LONDON.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>
                  <hi>Beloued</hi> in Chriſt
<hi>Jeſus:</hi>
               </salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T</hi> is the promiſe of the Word, that the
<hi>righteous</hi> ſhall be in euerlaſting remembrance,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 112.6.</note> as regiſtred in the booke of
<hi>eternall</hi> life, ſo graciouſly mentioned to the ioy of poſterity in <hi>this</hi> life.<note place="margin">Chriſoſt:</note> The beſt
<hi>monument</hi> is not in ſtately houſes, ſtrong walls, high Towers, glorious Sepulchers,<note place="margin">Antomin: <hi>1.</hi> P. Tit. <hi>2.</hi> C. <hi>9.</hi> S. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> but in righteous actions, grounded vpon
<hi>memory,</hi> which conſidering the infirmity of nature, loſſe by ſinne, examples of the good, folly of the wicked, neceſſity of the miſerable, and looking vpon God, as a Creatour, Redeemer, Rewarder, maketh a man liue according to his will reuealed in his Word;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mic.</hi> 6.8.</note> in doing <hi>iuſtly,</hi> louing
<hi>mercy,</hi> and walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>humbly.</hi> The memoriall of ſuch a one I
<pb facs="tcp:15638:3"/>preſent to you (and to thoſe whoſoeuer ſhall reade this paſſage from <hi>birth</hi> to <hi>death</hi>) in Sir
<hi>William Byrde</hi> deceaſed and gone to the <hi>Lord,</hi> whom I know
<hi>you</hi> eſteemed <hi>Inter raros &amp; paucos ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellentiſſimae gratiae viros,</hi> Amongst thoſe few choiſe <hi>pearles</hi> of excellent parts,<note place="margin">Aug. de Cyp. li. <hi>6.</hi> de Baptiſmo</note> left in theſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caying times. Vnperfect it is, and this <hi>birth</hi> had died as ſoone as it had beene borne (<hi>without preſſing</hi>) had not I perceiued how tender it was taken among ſome, and earneſtly deſired to be publiſhed by others. We ſhall learne to liue well by remembring our
<hi>death,</hi> and wee ſhall liue to <hi>God</hi> if we dye to the world. As long as I am in this <hi>Tabernacle</hi> I ſhall put you in remembrance of this,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Peter</hi> 1.13.</note> that you may loue the
<hi>Lord</hi> your <hi>God,</hi> walke in his wayes, keepe his commaundements, ſtatutes, iudgments, &amp; liue, &amp; multiply, &amp; that the <hi>Lord</hi> our <hi>God</hi> may bleſſe you: and we may be preſerued and deliuered at the houre of <hi>death</hi> and day of <hi>iudgement.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>From the new Rents in your Pariſh,</hi>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Octob. 18. 1624.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Yours in Chriſt Jeſus, <hi>Samſon Price.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:15638:3"/>
            <head>THE TVVO TVVINS OF <hi>BIRTH</hi> AND <hi>DEATH.</hi>
            </head>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Lord Ieſus begin and end.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>ECCLES. 3.2.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <q>
                     <p>A time to be borne, and a time to dye.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T was a diuine confeſſion of that ſweet Singer of Iſrael, holy King <hi>Dauid,</hi> a man con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning whom GOD did ſweare in his holineſſe,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſ.</hi> 89: 33.</note> that he would not ſuffer his faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe to faile him: <hi>His glory is great in thy ſaluation, honour and maieſtie haſt thou layde vpon him.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſ.</hi> 21.5.</note> Great were his <hi>deliuer ances from</hi> the Iawe of the Lyon, Pawe of the Beare, Iauelin of Saul, Speare of Goliath; <hi>from the</hi> Counſaile of Achitophell, Slaunder of Doeg, Reuiling of Shemei, Mouth of the Sword, <hi>from the</hi> murraine of his Subiects, multiplicity
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:15638:4"/>of his ſins, &amp; the rebellion of his ſon
<hi>Abſolon. Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable</hi> were his dignities <hi>in</hi> the loue of his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, glorious wearing of a Crowne, triumphant victories ouer his enemies. Hee was <hi>higher</hi> then the Kings of the earth:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſ.</hi> 89.27.</note> ſuch a <hi>ſonne</hi> did the Lord ſend him: <hi>Salomon</hi> a King, paſſing all the Kings of the earth in riches &amp; wiſdome,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Ch.</hi> 9.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 2.
<hi>Sam.</hi> 12.24 <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 1.1. 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.25</note> called <hi>Salomon</hi> by his father <hi>Dauid,</hi> when <hi>Bethſheba</hi> had borne him: the <hi>Preacher</hi> by himſelfe in the fore-front of this booke, and <hi>Iedidiah</hi> by <hi>Nathan</hi> the Prophet, by whoſe hand the Lord ſent ſo to name him.<note place="margin">Hier. in Eccleſ. orig. in Can. Am. pro. in Lu. Salonius vien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nenſis in Prou.</note> Three names agreeable to three bookes hee wrote, <hi>Salomon</hi> to that of the Prouerbs, the <hi>Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher</hi> to Eccleſiaſtes, <hi>Iedidiah</hi> to his Canticles: the <hi>Prouerbs</hi> containing morrall Inſtructions, the <hi>Preacher</hi> many naturall ſecrets,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Prou.</hi> 4.1.3.</note> his
<hi>Canticles</hi> the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernaturall myſterie of that marriage betwixt Chriſt and his Church.<note place="margin">Tria volumina Salomonis miſle Cobel. th. Sir Haſirim. Heir. Praef. in Prou. Solom.</note> In the
<hi>Prouerbs</hi> as a Father he teacheth tender children the offices of life: in <hi>Eccleſiaſtes</hi> the young man that for all things hee muſt be brought to iudgement: in the <hi>Canticles,</hi> him that is growne to ſome perfection how to be ioyned with diuine embracings to God,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cant.</hi> 1.2.</note> and to be kiſſed with the kiſſes of his mouth. In the <hi>Prouerbs,</hi> hee teacheth how to liue in the world: In <hi>Eccleſiaſtes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hie. Prae. in Ec.</note> how to deſpiſe the world: In the <hi>Canticles,</hi> how to loue God aboue the world. As <hi>Salomon,</hi> he wrote his Prouerbs, a King of peace giuing lawes, which being kept by vs, ſhall work internall, externall, eternall peace for vs, peace with our ſelues, neighbours, God. As a
<hi>Preacher</hi>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:15638:4"/>he wrote his Eccleſiaſtes: for no doctrine more fit for the Pulpit, and to be preached to the whole world, then mans mortality the chiefe ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect of the booke. As Gods <hi>fauourite,</hi> hee wrote the Canticles, containing the mutuall loue of Chriſt and his Church.
<hi>King Dauid</hi> was Gods beloued, and hence comes his name,<note place="margin">Dauid of <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> Dod Amor. Amicus. Dilec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus.</note> his ſonne <hi>Salomon</hi> was ſo, a wiſe ſonne of a wiſe father, a Prophet from a Prophet: for howſoeuer the ſpirit of prophecie goeth not euer by inheritance and ſucceſſion;<note place="margin">Baſil.</note> yet
<hi>Dauid</hi> by prayer obtained this bleſſing, to haue a ſonne like himſelfe, a ſonne by generation, and a ſonne by ſimilitude. <hi>King Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> delighted to teach tranſgreſſours the wayes of God, that ſinners might be conuerted:<note place="margin">Pſ. <hi>51.13.</hi> Prou.
<hi>1.2.</hi> Bede Ecleſ. <hi>12.14.</hi>
                  </note> ſo King <hi>Salomon</hi> wrote to make men know wiſdome and inſtruction, and to perceiue the words of vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, how men ſhould liue according to the truth of knowledge: direct their intentions, and gouerne their actions: For God ſhall bring euery worke into iudgement, with euery ſecret thing, whether it be good or whether it be euill. <hi>Thales</hi> therfore (anſwered well, when demanded what was the wiſeſt amongſt creatures: <hi>Time</hi> (ſaid he) for it findeth out all things. <hi>O then</hi> that we were wiſe, that we vnderſtood this, that we would con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider our latter end.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Deut.</hi>
37.29.</note> 
                  <hi>Things paſt</hi> muſt be conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, the good omitted,<note place="margin">Patritins de tranſitu animae ad Deum.</note> not prouiding for a time to come, neglecting the day of grace, deſiſting from doing good: the euill committed againſt God by diſobedience, our neighbours by hurt
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:15638:5"/>done, our ſelues by conſenting to ſinne: the time loſt which is precious, a benefit from God, irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocable: <hi>Things preſent</hi> muſt be conſidered, the ſhortneſſe of life which flyeth as a ſhadow, fadeth as a flower, is onely certaine in vncertainty: the worlds vanity, whereby the couetous are decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, the carnall led, the proud caught: the ſpace giuen to repent, wherein our eſtate ſhould be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred, our paſſage conſidered, our good fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeene. <hi>Things to come</hi> muſt be conſidered, the gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing vp of our account, when wee muſt anſwere for our thoughts, words, works, the day of death which is at hand ſure, vnſure: the day of iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which is the laſt doome, to the euill feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, to the good ioyfull. <hi>This</hi> was the ſong <hi>of Moſes,</hi> not onely merely propheticall, as <hi>Rabo, Paulus</hi> would haue it, but exhortatory alſo. This is the wiſdome from <hi>aboue,</hi> making men pure, peaceable, gentle, eaſie to be entreated, full of mercy and good fruits,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iam.</hi> 3.17.</note> without partiality, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out hypocriſie. <hi>Other</hi> wiſedome periſheth, the wiſdome of the <hi>ſerpent</hi> in a curſe,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſ.</hi>
29.14.</note> the wiſdome of the <hi>Phariſies</hi> in a woe, the wiſdome of <hi>Achitophel</hi> in folly, of <hi>Nimrod</hi> in confuſion, of the
<hi>vniuſt</hi> ſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in expulſion, the wiſedome of <hi>Iezabel</hi> in death. <hi>Moſes</hi> prayed for this heauenly wiſdome: So teach vs to number our dayes,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſ.</hi> 9.12.</note> that wee may apply our hearts vnto wiſdome:<note place="margin">Hier. ep.
<hi>139.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Nothing</hi> ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiueth men, as to be ignorant of the paces of their life, and to promiſe long times to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues; vnleſſe we thinke vpon death we can neuer
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:15638:5"/>faſhion our ſelues to a godly life.
<hi>Repentance</hi> hath no ſuch enemie, as to thinke that any time will ſerue to repent, <hi>Hardly</hi> can a man think of a ſhort life here and thinke euill, or of a long life and thinke well. The <hi>act</hi> of liuing well is very long, but life it ſelfe ſhort, and God would haue the time of death vnknowne vnto vs, becauſe wee ſhould be ready for him at all times, hauing no more certainty of one houre then another, yet <hi>Salomons</hi> leſſon ſhall make vs ready to leaue the world cheerefully, when we remember <hi>a time to be borne, and a time to dye.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A <hi>text</hi> ſhewing the ſhort <hi>progreſſe</hi> of mans life, his inconſtancie and mortality who commeth vp and is cut downe like a flower, flyeth as it were a ſhadow, and neuer continueth in one ſtay: in the midſt of life is in death, whirling by a ſwift wheele, which ſhould admoniſh vs, that we haue a ſet time for our taske, the
<hi>clocke</hi> counting our houres, and ſhould worke out our ſaluation with feare and trembling, while we haue light, leaſt we be benighted, and our eyes ſhut, and wee ſleepe in death. A great <hi>taske</hi> it is, and we ſhould not loſe one minute, but make a good vſe of time, and ſeeing we were borne to glorifie God, and muſt dye, wee ſhould labour that after death wee may liue for euer with him in glory, becauſe there is <hi>a time to be borne, and a time to dye,</hi> as ſure as wee haue beene borne, ſo ſure we muſt dye.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Oritur Mori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur.</note> Birth and Death are
<hi>Twinnos.</hi> The <hi>ſumme</hi> of the words is, the Reuolution of time, or watch
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:15638:6"/>of time, or the Race of life, or Mans mortality, or his pilgrimage, conſiſting of two parts:</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. Vpon <hi>his birth,</hi> a time to be borne.</item>
                  <item>2. Vpon <hi>his death,</hi> and a time to dye.</item>
               </list>
               <p>The <hi>firſt,</hi> ſheweth vs his comming forth, the
<hi>ſecond,</hi> his returning backe. In the <hi>firſt</hi> ſee his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning: In the <hi>ſecond</hi> his ending. The <hi>firſt,</hi> ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth his day: the <hi>ſecond,</hi> threatneth a night. Here is the
<hi>Prologue</hi> and <hi>Epilogue</hi> of the ſtate of man, wherein, firſt his Birth commeth to bee conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Prima pars. Caietan.</note> 
                  <hi>A time to be borne.</hi> Amongſt <hi>Salomons couples;</hi> which are 14. in this Chapter, the <hi>foure firſt</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarieties concerning the generation and corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of men, plants, other creatures, and things made by Art: the
<hi>foure next</hi> concerning the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectable good: the <hi>other three</hi> a profitable good: and the <hi>three laſt,</hi> humane ſociety:
<hi>Firſt,</hi> heere is mention made of the Birth and Death,<note place="margin">Nyſſen &amp; O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lym<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iod.</note> to rowze vp the ſluggard, to raiſe vp the worldly minded men, who neglect things future, remembring them, that becauſe they were borne, they muſt dye; as <hi>Moſes,</hi> vvho hauing vvritten his booke of <hi>Geneſis,</hi> the beginning, creation, production of creatures, vvrote an <hi>Exodus</hi> next to that, a going out. No man muſt murmur againſt Gods proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence: It is not in the
<hi>power</hi> of man to come into the vvorld,<note place="margin">Hugo Victori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus.</note> nor in his diſpoſition to depart out of the vvorld. A
<hi>diuine</hi> hand ruleth all, euery thing hath its ſeaſon, as a time ordained by God. The creature is gouerned by the <hi>Creatour. Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:15638:6"/>that came downe from heauen, firſt appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in the glimpſe of the rudiments of nature; vvhen the lavv came it vvas in the infancie,<note place="margin">Tertul. de Virg. Veland. c. <hi>10.</hi>
                  </note> vvhen the Goſpell vvas preached, it had a flouriſhing youth; and at the comming dovvne of the holy Ghoſt, it grevv to more maturity. <hi>When</hi> the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of time vvas come,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gal.</hi>
4.4.</note> God ſent forth his Son. It is folly for men to murmure, that they were borne at ſuch times and not other: vve are borne at Gods pleaſure, and his periods of time. There is a time of <hi>conception,</hi> &amp; a time of birth; For that hath not euer a birth, which hath had a concep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, though ſomtimes one word be vſed for ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the birth for the conception, as that which ſhall be borne of thee ſhall be called the Son of God:<note place="margin">Lorinus in tex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum. Luk. <hi>1.35.</hi>
                  </note> and ſomtime it ſignifieth any increaſing, as
<q>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Naſcere Dardanio promiſſum ſemen Iulo</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Tu modo naſcenti puero—caſtae faue Lucina:</hi>
                     </l>
                  </q> And that Sometimes <hi>Birth</hi> is taken for creation, as that,<note place="margin">Martial l. <hi>6.</hi> Epig. <hi>7.</hi> 
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irg. Aeglog. <hi>4.</hi> Iob <hi>15.7.</hi>
                  </note> Art thou the firſt man that was
<hi>borne?</hi> Vnderſtood of <hi>Adam:</hi> But here in the proper ſignification oppoſed to Death, and limited by God,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 73.9.</note> who diſpoſeth of all things though ſome ſet their mouth againſt the heauens, and caſt the faults they commit vpon the <hi>Planets</hi> vnder vvhich they vvere borne,<note place="margin">Amb. &amp; Euth. in illud Pſal.</note> neuer conſidering how prouidence gouerneth time, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer referring any thing to their owne corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.
<hi>God</hi> hath ſent vs into the vvorld to vſe our time vvell, that vvhither vve liue vvee liue vnto the Lord, or dye, vve may dye in the Lord, ſo vve ſhall exchange a troubleſome life for a peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:15638:7"/>a temporall for an eternall. <hi>Man</hi> is borne miſerable. For other creatures which are but <hi>baſe borne</hi> in reſpect of man; haue couerings to defend them, and Bucklers to offend their enemies. <hi>Fiſhes</hi> of the Sea haue ſhels,<note place="margin">Pli. nat. hiſt. li. <hi>7.</hi> proem.</note> Trees of the Forreſt haue knotty barkes, Beaſts of the field hard hides, Bees ſtings, Hogs briſtles, Hedgehogs prickles, Beares rough hayre, Birds feathers, Fiſhes ſcales, Sheepe fleeces, Serpents ſtings, Cockes ſpurres, Elephants and Bores teeth and tuskes, <hi>yet</hi> man commeth from the <hi>priſon</hi> of his mothers wombe as a poore worm,<note place="margin">Ar. l. <hi>3.</hi> de gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat. animal. c. <hi>4.</hi>
                  </note> Yea <hi>nudiſsimum omnium anima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lium:</hi> Moſt naked of all liuing creatures. Hee en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters into the world bathed in bloud, an image of ſinne,<note place="margin">Dr. Wilk.</note> his firſt ſong is the <hi>Lamentation</hi> of a ſinner, weeping and ſobbing, the
<hi>mother</hi> lyeth, by but halfe flaine by the birth, and when ſhee looketh vpon the fruit of her labour pranked vp, it is as the Thiefe when he is pardoned, looketh backe to the ſtring that was like to ſtrangle him: and knoweth this childe had beene her death, had not <hi>God</hi> giuen her a ſafe deliuerance in the great danger of child-birth. The <hi>childe</hi> being borne, requireth nouriſhment, and the mother ſhould doe this, if her breaſts be as able bottles, and her ſtrength ſufficient, and no maine let to hinder the nurſing of her owne childe: yet often (vpon a needleſſe wantonneſſe) the mothers ſend abroad their Infants to ſtrange
<hi>Nurſes</hi> and remote places, not enduring to embrace little children in their armes, which <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelfe did, hauing beene
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:15638:7"/>once a <hi>childe,</hi> and wrapped in ſwadling cloathes, but rather wil embrace a Whelp or Puppy, worſe then the Sea <hi>monſters,</hi> they draw out the breaſt,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>La.</hi> 4.3.</note> and giue ſucke to their young ones: yet if this young <hi>Gallant</hi> bee nurſed by his owne mothers paps, and tender, and onely beloued in her ſight,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pro.</hi>
4.3.</note> as once borne in her womb, and euer borne in her heart; tender in her eyes, becauſe ſhee is euer ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly carefull and fearefull of him: what is hee borne to but a ſucceſſion of miſerable times, if he outliue the birth? for he might haue dyed from the wombe, and giuen vp the ghoſt when hee came out of the belly:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iob</hi> 3.11.12.</note> the knees might haue pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uented him, and the breaſts from ſucking. What is
<hi>Infancie</hi> but an Apprentiſhip of ſeauen yeares infirmity,<note place="margin">Jſidore reckous <hi>6.</hi> ages. Infan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, Puerility, Mans ſtate. youth, grauity, o'de age. Marcius Aure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius: Galen ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth but
<hi>5.</hi> Childhood to <hi>15.</hi> yeares, Adoleſcencie to <hi>25.</hi> Luſty youth to <hi>35.</hi> Mans age to <hi>49.</hi> The laſt olde age.</note> wherein there is no vſe of expreſſing almoſt a reaſonable ſoule? <hi>Childhood</hi> to 10. but an vntoward phantaſticall toying; ſhake the rod, it is perſecution: <hi>Mans</hi> eſtate to 28. but headie, aduenturous, voluptuous, paſſionate, prodigall. <hi>Youth</hi> to 50. but a ſeaſon, wherein Nature reareth againſt him a more furious combat, and all the vices of the world there plant their ſiege: <hi>Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitie</hi> or vnweldineſſe to 70, bring all the diſeaſes that euer Chriſt came to cure. <hi>Olde age</hi> hauing no ſtint as the other, becauſe the remaines of life are referred to this, yet the dregges onely and powder of mans life, and a continuall neceſſary expectation of death. Thus man neuer continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth conſtant, and ſcarce is his life a life in his mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table conditions, toſſed by time, which conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:15638:8"/>runnes on and is irreuocable. <hi>THIS</hi> is our <hi>wiſedome</hi> to apprehend it, and not neglect or abuſe it. All Gods workes haue <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, a time and ſeaſon, and we ſhould make our time ſeaſonable, for it is an high part of wiſdome to follow opportunity: Natures Secretarie the
<hi>Phiſitian</hi> looketh at this, and euery man ſheweth himſelfe wiſe or fooliſh in this.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Temperibus medicina valet: Data tempore proſunt</l>
                  <l>Et data non apto tempore vina nocent.<note place="margin">Ou.
<hi>1.</hi> de remed. amor.</note>
                  </l>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pitacus</hi> beſt aduiſe was <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: know the ſeaſon. He that is yong in yeares may be old in houres if he looſe not time, and as fit for iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment as inuention, for counſaile as execution.
<hi>If</hi> he remember the <hi>times,</hi> he will not <hi>embrace</hi> more then he can hold, ſtirre more then he can quiet, flie to the end without conſideration of the meanes and degrees, vſe extreame remedies at firſt, be like an vnruly <hi>horſe</hi> that will neither ſtoppe nor turne.
<hi>Time</hi> brings changes and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is good to be wiſe in time: The
<hi>Antients</hi> painted this as an Image on a ſwift wheele, hauing feathers at the foot, running ſwiftly in a round, rough at the foretop, bald behind, when offring it ſelfe eaſie to be taken, afterward impoſſible: ſome as a goodly <hi>Boy</hi> with his haires hanging o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer his eyes:<note place="margin">Politian. in Miſcell. c. <hi>49.</hi> Iohn Tzetzes in hiſtorijs. Pier. l. <hi>14.</hi> pag. <hi>130.</hi> Id. l. <hi>56.</hi> p.
<hi>536</hi>
                  </note> ſome paint it deafe without eares, reaching a ſword to him that ſhall follow it. The <hi>Egiptians</hi> deſcribe it by a
<hi>Serpent</hi> ſtreatching it ſelfe in length wreaths &amp; foulds, the long courſes of dayes and yeares, creeping along without
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:15638:8"/>noyſe. Others by a ſithe repreſent it,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Id. l.</hi> 52. <hi>p.</hi> 505 <hi>Id. l.</hi> 44.
<hi>p.</hi> 437</note> becauſe it moweth, reapeth, cutteth all things down. Others by a <hi>Poplar</hi> tree hauing leaues of two colours, ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnifying the day and night. Others by a <hi>Starre,</hi> for nothing ſo keepeth the appointed times as the heauenly bodies, and ſo ſhould wee from that globe of examples: For our times runne on and ſlippe away and we cannot hold in the ſwift poſt of our dayes.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">Ouid.</note>Tempora labuntur, tacitiſque ſeneſcimus annis,</l>
                  <l>Et fugiunt fraeno non remorante dies.</l>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Time</hi> conſumeth wit, fame, youth, honour, old age, ſtrength. Nothing liueth here but is ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to the lawe of time; It is the <hi>watch</hi> of the morning, ſentinell of the night, ruine of proud buildings, ſpoile of antiquities, tamer of wilde beaſts, <hi>waſter</hi> of huge ſtones with ſmall droppes. It maketh an <hi>Embrio</hi> to become a child, a child a man, and an old man as it were a child againe: The time of
<hi>birth</hi> we ſee deſcribed by the wiſe man;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Woſd.</hi> 7.2.3.4.</note> a faſhioning there was of vs to be fleſh in the wombes of our mother in the time of tenne moneths; and being borne, we drew in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon aire and fell vpon the earth which is of like nature; the firſt voice we vttered was <hi>crying:</hi> we then come to be nurſed in ſwadling <hi>clothes</hi> and that with cares, and no
<hi>King</hi> had another begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of birth.<note place="margin">Natiuitas mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rabilis. Ier. <hi>23.5.</hi>
                  </note> There is an <hi>admirable</hi> Natiuity wherein fleſh is borne without ſpot, there is his purity, as in
<hi>Chriſts</hi> birth arighteous bra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ch, a child of a <hi>Virgin,</hi> there is the nouelty: <hi>God</hi> of a woman,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:15638:9"/>there is humility, the <hi>higheſt</hi> himſelfe ſhall eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh her:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſ.</hi>
7.14.</note> 
                  <hi>Fruit</hi> of a Rod, there is our commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; vnto vs a child is borne,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſ.</hi> 87.5.</note> 
                  <hi>borne</hi> as an example of humility,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſ.</hi> 9.6.</note> teſtimony of verity, figure of loue, couenant of reconciliation: <hi>but</hi> our Natiuity is <hi>miſerable</hi> becauſe vile and vncleane: what is hee which is borne of a woman that hee ſhould be righteous?<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Miſerabilis. Iob.</hi> 15.14.</note> poenal and inflamed by hell, clouded with darkenes and paſſing as a ſhadowe:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iob.</hi> 3.6.</note> In this birth man hath another following making him blind in his birth,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioh.</hi> 9.1.</note> vnworthy to teach others, weake to doe good,<note place="margin">Vituperabilis.</note> fraile to reſiſt euill: we haue had time to be <hi>borne,</hi> and as a man that hath paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ouer a dangerous bridge if hee turne bake quaketh to remember the danger he was in; ſo if we looke backe vpon the danger we eſcaped till our birth, and in it, we may ſay as King <hi>Dauid Thou art hee that tooke me out of the wombe,</hi> but few conſider the vſe of their birth and ſo much abuſe time,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſ.</hi> 22.9.</note> that better it had bene for them they had neuer bene borne.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> This then iuſtly
<hi>reproueth</hi> many who miſpend their time in chambering and wantoneſſe,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.13.</note> glut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tony and drunkenes, and vitious games, hauing no portion to themſelues or poſterity in earth, neuer thinking of a portion in heauen, hauing no conſcience for their ſoules, no diſcretion for their goods. <hi>Some</hi> complaine of the
<hi>iniquity</hi> of the times and no whit mend themſelues: ſay not, Former times were better, thy vertues make good times,<note place="margin">Hic in Ecclſ. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> thy vices bad. All things are <hi>others,</hi> time

<pb n="13" facs="tcp:15638:9"/>onely is our owne, yet haſteneth, and therefore ſhould not be waſted away, as by him, who being asked how long he had liued? anſwered,<note place="margin">Stob. ſe. <hi>9.</hi> de Simouide.</note> 
                  <hi>a very little time though many yeares:</hi> Or as thoſe lewd ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants who hauing a candle allowed them to goe to bed withal, ſpend it in carding, dicing, or drin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king. What a <hi>curſe</hi> is it to ſpend al thy time in va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, and to ſend thy hoary head to thy graue in ignorance and follie? <hi>Wilt</hi> thou giue Sathan the fineſt of thy flower and ſweeteſt of thy wine, and preſent the bran and dregges of thy dottage to thy <hi>Lord?</hi> wilt thou lay the heauieſt burthen vpon the weakeſt beaſt, and force old age (ſo feeble that it cannot beare it ſelfe) to beare all the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then of thy Repentance? <hi>O take heed,</hi> for when the ſtrong man is growne ſtronger by praeſcription, the rotten tabernacle is ready to fall downe: cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome hath turned infirmity into nature; ſinne is ſoaked into ſubſtance: when thy bones ſhall be full of the ſinnes of thy youth, then to repent it will be hard, if not impoſſible. <hi>Did</hi> not wee bring ſinne enough with vs into the world to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne vs? we muſt all confeſſe as he did, <hi>Behold</hi> I was ſhapen in inquinity and in ſinne did my mother conceaue me: words which <hi>Dauid</hi> vttered,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſ.</hi> 51.5. 2. <hi>Kin.</hi> 18.42.</note> as
<hi>Eliah</hi> when he put his face betweene his knees, for ſo is the child in the wombe. <hi>Boaſt</hi> not of thy goods, Inheritance, countenance, and blood by thy Parents, it is tainted with ſin: this is the poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.<note place="margin">Pineda in Iob. <hi>15.24.</hi> Hipoer. lib. de natura pueri.</note> Wee had <hi>Birth</hi> from our mothers, but with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all the reward of ſinne, death; clothes and wrap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:15638:10"/>from the but withall nakedneſſe and ſhame. What muſt be done, but as that <hi>woman</hi> ſicke of the bloody iſſue, hauing beene long phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicked, but ill handled of the Phyſitians, hauing ſuffered many things of many Phyſitians, and ſpent all ſhe had and nothing bettered, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther grew worſe;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mar.</hi>
5.26.27</note> when ſhe heard of <hi>Ieſus,</hi> came to be phyſiked a new of him; So we who are thus baſe borne, muſt take our time to be borne a new. This is an <hi>Honourable</hi> and commendable birth if we reſpect the cauſes.<note place="margin">Natiuitas com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendabilis.</note> 
                  <hi>Faith:</hi> whoſoeuer beleeueth that <hi>Ieſus</hi> is the Chriſt is borne of God.
<hi>Loue:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. <hi>Io.</hi> 5.1.1.<hi>Io.</hi> 4.7.1.
<hi>Io.</hi> 3.9.</note> Euery one that loueth is borne of God and knoweth God.
<hi>Righteouſneſſe:</hi> whoſoeuer is borne of God doth not commit ſinne, preſumptuoſly, deſperatly, impenitently. It is an honourable birth if wee reſpect the <hi>effects,</hi> to <hi>conquer</hi> the world; whatſoeuer is borne of God ouercom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth the world,<note place="margin">1.
<hi>10.</hi> 5.4. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.3.</note> to bring to <hi>heauen,</hi> for except a man be borne againe hee cannot ſee the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God.
<hi>This</hi> maketh new men, new affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, giueth another ſpirit, another will, a loa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of the world, a loue of God. It cauſeth vs not ſo much to obſerue dayes, and moneths, and times, and yeares, as to know <hi>The TIME</hi> that now it is high time to awake out of ſleepe,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gala.</hi> 4.10. <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.22.</note> for now is our ſaluation neerer then when we belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued.<note place="margin">Sicut nec ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pillus de oapite ſie nec momentu ſeribis de tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pore: Bar.</note>
                  <hi>This</hi> maketh vs good husbands and euer to thinke vpon our reckoning, and to conſider that as not a haire falleth to the ground without pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence, ſo neither a moment of our time is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>accountable:
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:15638:10"/>
                  <hi>How</hi> buſie was the <hi>Deuill</hi> aboue a thouſand yeares ſince, becauſe he knew he had but a ſhort time?
<hi>Will</hi> you plant, build, buy,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Reu.</hi>
12.22.</note> ſell onely for the world, and doe nothing for eterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty?
<hi>Will</hi> you be prodigall of the golden dayes gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vs to redeeme time, and let heauen flie away and hell ſteale on? Bee not lulled a ſleepe in eaſe, mirth, proſperity, as the <hi>Dalilah</hi> of the world or fleſh, or Deuill perſwade. <hi>Sathan</hi> will come with fearefull arreſt and ſeaſe vpon thee in ſicke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, weakeneſſe, diſcontent, as the Rauen vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the fainting ſheepe; and write, and vrge, and open bitter, vnanſwerable, terrible things againſt thee: O then that men would flie out of the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt of <hi>Babylon,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Reuela.</hi>
2.22.</note> and deliuer euery man his ſoule that hee be not cut off in iniquity, for there is a <hi>TIME</hi> of the Lords vengeance.
<hi>Iezebell</hi> had her ſpace to repent of her fornication and repented not, therefore a bed of tribulation is threatened her. <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> not knowing the time of her viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, had their enemies to caſt a trench about them, compaſſe them round, keepe them in on euery ſide, lay them euen with the ground,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luk.</hi> 19.44.</note> and their children within them, and not to leaue one ſtone vpon another.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Am.</hi> 5.13.</note> 
                  <hi>If</hi> we ſee the <hi>TIME</hi> when the prudent keepe ſilence becauſe it is an euill time:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mic.</hi> 2.3.</note> 
                  <hi>when</hi> men worke euill vpon their beds, and couet fields, and take them by violence becauſe it is an euill time: <hi>when</hi> men dwell in their fieled houſes, and yet ſay the time is not come, that the Lords houſe ſhould be built:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hagg.</hi> 1.2.</note> 
                  <hi>when</hi> being poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:15638:11"/>with Deuils and reproued, they crie as thoſe did to <hi>Ieſus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 8.29.</note> what haue we to doe with thee, Art thou come hither to torment vs before the time? <hi>When</hi> thoſe perillous times come wherein men are louers of themſelues, couetous, boaſters, proud,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Tim.</hi>
3.1.2.</note> blaſphemers, diſobedient to Parents, vnthankefull, vnholy;
<hi>Wherein</hi> when for the time men ought to be teachers, they haue need that one teach themagain,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.12.</note> which be the firſt principles of the Oracle of Gods: <hi>When</hi> the laſt times bring forth thoſe who walke after their owne vngodly luſtes,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iude</hi> 18.19.</note> ſeparating themſelues; ſenſuall, hauing not the ſpirit. <hi>Let vs pray,</hi> It is TIME for thee Lord to worke,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſ.</hi> 119.126.</note> for they haue made voyd thy Lawe.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Job</hi> 22:16.</note>
                  <hi>He</hi> ſhall cut them downe out of time and ouerflowe their foundation with a floud: their falſe Gods cannot ariſe and ſaue them in the time of trouble:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jer.</hi> 2.27.</note> 
                  <hi>They</hi> ſhall fall when others fall. When they are viſited and ſhall be caſt downe,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jer.</hi> 6.15.</note> 
                  <hi>They</hi> ſhall be ſmitten and haue no healing; looke for peace and there ſhall be no good, for a time of healing and behold trouble:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jer.</hi>
14.19.</note> 
                  <hi>They</hi> ſhall be like a thraſhing flower, for the Lord ſeeth it is time to thraſh them, <hi>yet a little while</hi> and the time of their harueſt ſhall come: An end is come, it watcheth for them,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ier.</hi> 51.33.</note> the time is come, the day of trouble is neere: a time of trouble, ſuch as neuer was ſince there was a Nation,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ezek.</hi> 7.7.</note> euen to that ſame time.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Da.</hi> 12.1.</note> 
                  <hi>Man</hi> knoweth not his time; As the fiſhes that are taken in an euill net, and as the birds that are caught in the ſnare, ſo are the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:15638:11"/>ſonnes of men ſnared in an euill time, when it fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth ſuddainly vpon them.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ecleſ.</hi>
9.12.</note> The <hi>fiſh</hi> is cheerefull deuouring the bayt not ſeeing the hooke, but the fiſher-man drawing him vp, torments the bowels and dragges it to deſtruction.<note place="margin">Auguſt. de ago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne Chriſti. cap.
<hi>7.</hi>
                  </note> So many runne away with preſumptuous ſinnes, but the time ſhall come that they ſhall feele the plagues of it; when time ſhal be no longer. One woe ſhall be paſt and another woe come quickly: from death to iudgement, from iudgement to hell.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Reu.</hi>
10.11.14</note> They may come vp as <hi>flouds,</hi> their waters may moue as the riuers, they may ſaye, <hi>we will couer the earth;</hi> they may rage with their Charets, but when the day of vengeance commeth, in vaine ſhall they vſe many medicines, for they ſhall not be cured; their crye ſhall fill the land, they ſhall be ſwept away when the <hi>Lord</hi> driueth them, they ſhall appeare to haue beene but a <hi>noyſe</hi> when they haue paſſed the time appointed.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jer.</hi>
46.17.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> Our <hi>Inſtruction</hi> muſt be, not to walke as fooles, but circumſpectly, as wiſe, redeeming the time, becauſe the dayes are euill: wee are borne of wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ep.</hi> 5.16.</note> of few dayes, full of trouble.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioh.</hi> 14.1.</note> Let vs <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member</hi> how ſhort our time is: what man is hee that liueth and ſhall not ſee death?<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſ</hi> 89.47.48.</note> Be not ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much wicked, neither bee thou fooliſh: why ſhouldeſt thou die before thy time?<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 7.17.</note>
               </p>
               <q>Stat ſua cuique dies.</q>
               <p>Euery mans dayes are determined,<note place="margin">Virgil.
<hi>10.</hi> Aeneid.</note> the number of his moneths is with God, he hath appointed him his bounds that he cannot paſſe:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioh.</hi> 14.5.</note> this is a
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:15638:12"/>meaſure of his dayes, in reſpect of Gods
<hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience</hi> and prouidence,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal</hi>
39.4.</note> but in reſpect of the courſe of <hi>nature,</hi> the threed of life which might haue beene lengthned is cut off by Gods com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand for ſinne, and men liue not out halfe their dayes:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi>
55.23.</note> as that <hi>Biſhop</hi> applyed this texte in his time,<note place="margin">Bernardinus to. <hi>2.</hi> in Qua. drageſimali de Euang. oetern. Do. <hi>2.</hi> quadra. ſerm. <hi>17.</hi> a. <hi>3.</hi> cap.
<hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> when in <hi>Catalonia</hi> a citty neare <hi>Valentia,</hi> a ſtrippling of 18. hauing beene diſobedient to his parents, and ſo fell to robbing, and being execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted on the tree, and thus remaining for a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctacle to diſobedient children; on the next mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, a <hi>Beard</hi> and gray haires appeared on him, which the people hearing of, and wondring how ſuddainely theſe ſhould come to a young dead body, and vrging how young he was at his death; the <hi>Biſhop</hi> ſaid, he ſhould haue liued to be ſo old as hee appeared then, had he not beene diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient. Thus the Lord threatneth the family of <hi>Eli,</hi> all the increaſe of thine houſe ſhall dye in the flower of their age.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Sam.</hi>
3.33.</note> 
                  <hi>He</hi> dyeth before his time who dyeth vnwillingly, not prepared, not rype in yeares, though rype in ſinne; which haſteneth death and deſtruction as God threatned to the <hi>Amorrhites</hi> when their iniquity ſhould be full.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 15.16.</note>
                  <hi>Happy</hi> is he who can triumphe with that flagge of defiance againſt all enemies as St. <hi>Paul.</hi> Herein doe I excerciſe my ſelfe to haue alwayes a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience voyd of offence toward God and toward men.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 24.16.</note> 
                  <hi>Happy</hi> is he who euery night thinketh with himſelfe, a day is gone, a part of my time is cut off, ſo much leſſe haue I left of a ſhort and miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:15638:12"/>life. <hi>God</hi> hath appointed the time of life ſhort, in reſpect of <hi>proſperity</hi> and aduerſity in this world, that our appetite may be ſtirred to future things whereof here we haue but a taſte, as were the trees in Paradiſe and Manna; If theſe plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures belowe delight vs, how much more ſhall thoſe aboue?
<hi>Puniſhments</hi> here are but eſſayes of thoſe hereafter ordained for the wicked, as thoſe vppon the <hi>Sodomits, Chorah</hi> and his complices, and if the ſhort plagues of this life are feared; how much more thoſe of another? <hi>A little</hi> time we haue, that by little conſolations we may be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uited to glory, and by ſmall troubles feare grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. <hi>A little</hi> time is giuen vs, leaſt our troubles be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ouer long we ſhould deſpaire: onour ioyes, we ſhould neglect God.
<hi>Aduerſity</hi> ſometimes muſt exerciſe vs, elſe proſperity will pull vs down. There are but foure times, a time of <hi>deuiation</hi> as from
<hi>Adam</hi> to <hi>Moſes</hi> when death reigned:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.14.</note> a time of <hi>Reuocation</hi> from
<hi>Moſes</hi> to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> the Lawe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing added becauſe of tranſgreſſions: a time of <hi>Reconciliation</hi> from the birth of
<hi>Chriſt</hi> to the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the holy Ghoſt,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.19.</note> the ſpirit it ſelfe bearing witneſſe with our ſpirit that wee are the children of God; a time of
<hi>Peregrination</hi> from the ſending of the holy Ghoſt till the day of Iudgement,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.16.</note> while wee are at home in the body,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.7.</note> vve being ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent from the Lord.<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.7.</note> In this Pilgrimage we muſt walk by faith. The times are dangerous in regard of
<hi>troubles</hi> which muſt fail out, ſuch as neuer were ſince the begining of the world:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.21.</note> Of Sathans

<pb n="20" facs="tcp:15638:13"/>
                  <hi>libertie;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Reu.</hi> 20.8.</note> who being looſed, deceaued the Nations of the foure quarters of the earth: of the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of many
<hi>falſe</hi> Prophets riſing and decea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing many:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Math.</hi> 24.11.</note> of the <hi>rareneſſe</hi> of good men,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Math.</hi> 24.12.</note> iniquity abounding: the loue of many waxing cold. Let not the time runne away without obſeruation. Thinke vppon time <hi>paſt</hi> and be thankefull for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits receaued; Creation, Redemption, Iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation: repent for ſinne committed; imitate the godly: Think vppon the time <hi>preſent,</hi> the oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity vrging vs to worke while we haue time; the breuity compelling vs to be inſtant, the irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocability ſtirring vs vp to conſtancie. Thinke vpon the time to
<hi>come</hi> and prouide to giue a faire account.<note place="margin">Barn. de trip. cuſtodia. <hi>1.</hi> Cor. <hi>4.7.</hi>
                  </note> Nothing ought to be of ſo pretious eſteeme as time, it is Gods gift, we haue nothing but what we haue receaued; wee are anſwerable for it, and muſt deliuer backe all things in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber and weight: we muſt gaine according to the talentes deliuered vnto vs:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ecc.</hi> 42.7.</note> wee muſt growe in grace,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Math.</hi> 25.20.</note> 
                  <hi>And to this end</hi> as in bodily growth, there are 4. helpes, ſo in a ſpirituall: There is
<hi>nouriſhment</hi> in the wombe, here is a proficiencie of knowe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge; there we are brought into the light of the world, here we ſhewe forth ſome fruits of the il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumination of Baptiſme: there is <hi>milke</hi> giuen vnto vs, here the word of God deliuered out of both Teſtaments: there wee are carryed to our <hi>Parents</hi> table, here we come to the Supper of the Lord, our heart and our fleſh reioycing; that <hi>Nowe</hi> is the accepted time:<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.2.</note> now is the day of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:15638:13"/>wherein God the Father begetteth vs, the Church our mother conceaueth vs: The ſeede whereby we are borne againe is the word: the nurſes to feede, weane, cheriſh vs, are the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the Goſpell, and preaching is the food we muſt require, which will make vs new creatures, haue new ſoules, affections, members; a new heart, hand, eares, eye: but if there be no <hi>appetite</hi> in vs after this; we are a
<hi>Golgotha,</hi> hauing a name to liue but are dead in ſinne and dead in deſires, <hi>vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borne</hi> and <hi>better vnborne then vntaught.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Was it miraculous for <hi>Elias</hi> to liue forty dayes without foode of the body,<note place="margin">Animas portant mortuas in cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poribus viuis. Aug.</note> and ſhall we thinke to liue for euer if wee neglect the food of our ſoules, which ſhould nouriſh vs to life euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting, hauing a name to liue but are dead and carry about vs dead ſoules in liuing bodyes? <hi>Haue wee hereetofore liued an idle, prophane, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godlie life?</hi> O let vs liue the reſt of our time in the fleſh no longer to the luſts of men, but to the will of God, for the time paſt of our life (as the Apoſtle ſpeaketh) <hi>may ſuffice</hi> vs to haue walked in the will of the Gentiles, vvherein the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> allovveth not the former life but reproueth it:<note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.3.</note> It is like that, more ouer this vvas not enough for them that they erred in the knovvledge of
<hi>God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Non approbat ſed reprobat vitam praeteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam. Lyra.</note> but vvhereas they liued in the great vvarre of ignorance, thoſe ſo great plagues they called peace: and like that, <hi>O ye houſe of</hi> Iſrael,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Wiſd.</hi> 14.22.</note> let it ſuffice you of all your abominations.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ez.</hi> 44.6.</note> There is no loſſe to the loſſe of time: it is <hi>folly</hi> to expect
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:15638:14"/>time while we haue it before vs. Hee that hath life hath time, and this runns ſwifter then a Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers ſhuttle:
<hi>Remember</hi> how greiuous it will be to thinke vpon the neglect of time, as <hi>Titus Veſpaſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> meditated,<note place="margin">Suction.</note>
                  <hi>Amici diem perdidi:</hi> A day miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent is loſt. It was the lamentable Epitaph of <hi>Similis</hi> Captaine of the Guarde to the Emperour
<hi>Adrian</hi> after hee had retired himſelfe and liued priuatly ſeauen yeares in the country,<note place="margin">Xiphilinus in vita Adriani.</note> that hee had liued onely ſeauen yeares.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Hic iacet Similis: cuius aetas</l>
                  <l>Multorum annorum fuit, ipſe</l>
                  <l>Septem duntaxat annos vixit.</l>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Let</hi> vs conſider how long it is ſince wee were borne, and number our yeares, not from the time of our old birth, but <hi>New birth.</hi> Let vs often con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider how our time runnes on, let vs remember the day of DOOME, the end of this time, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gining of immortality to come.<note place="margin">2. <hi>Eſd.</hi> 7.43.</note> Let vs looke vpon our threefold diſeaſe, the begining, mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, end: our Natiuity, life, death, Our Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uity vncleane, our life peruerſe, our death dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous: Let the meditation of the <hi>birth</hi> of Chriſt purge our birth;<note place="margin">Bar: in tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitu malachiae peſſima mors peccatoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum Natiuitas mala, vita peior.</note> of his death deſtroy our death; of his life inſtruct our life. Our <hi>Natiuity</hi> hath bene ſinfull, let not our life be badde, leaſt our death be worſe: Let vs endeauour to dye the death of Saints by liuing as Gods beſt ſeruants: then pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious ſhall our death be in the ſight of the Lord, as the end of out labours, conſummation of our victories, the gate of life, an entrance into glory:
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:15638:14"/>Let vs get to bee <hi>borne</hi> againe, which is our new Regeneration in Body and Spirit.<note place="margin">Bar. declamat. &amp; apol. ad Guli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elmu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Abbatem.</note> We <hi>fell</hi> together in ſoule and body, but firſt muſt riſe in ſoule if we would be raiſed vp at the laſt day in bodyes to glory. Let vs firſt eſteeme our
<hi>ſoules</hi> and not as thoſe of the ſchoole of <hi>Hipocrates</hi> and <hi>Epicurus</hi> who neglect the ſoule and prouide only for the body, who feare not to commit ſin, but to endure ſhame. Let vs know that as farre as <hi>the ſpirit</hi> is aboue the fleſh, God aboue men, hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen aboue the earth, eternity aboue frailty; ſo farre is the new creation aboue the olde; the one is mortall and corruptible, the other immortall, from heauen, a worke of God, abiding for euer: This bringeth to life, the other to death, as it followeth the Birth here.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">PARS. </seg>II</label> And a time to dye.</head>
               <p>There are many reaſons why <hi>Death</hi> is come into the world: the <hi>diſobedience</hi> of Gods prohibition. Of the fruit of the tree in the middſt of the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, God hath ſaid, ye ſhall not eate leaſt ye dye.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.3.</note>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Malice</hi> of the Deuils temptation;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Wiſd.</hi> 7.24.</note> through enuie of the Deuill came death into the world, the <hi>folly</hi> of the womans condition: ſhe ſaw that the tree was good for food, pleaſant to the eyes, and a Tree to be deſired to make one wiſe, and tooke of the fruit thereof and did eate: The
<hi>mans</hi> greedy apprehenſion, and hee did eate:<note place="margin">ibid.</note> Hence ſome obſerue that <hi>mors</hi> comes of
<hi>mordeo,</hi> becauſe our firſt Parents did eate of that forbidden fruit.
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:15638:15"/>
                  <hi>A memorable</hi> puniſhment drawing a man from pryde:<note place="margin">Ecc. <hi>10.9.</hi> facile co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>temnit omnia qui nouit ſe moriturum. Aug. &amp; Hier</note> why is earth and aſhes proud? from <hi>co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetouſneſſe:</hi> Eaſily deſpiſeth a man the world when he ſeeth he muſt dye: <hi>from earthly pleaſures,</hi> cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption being the father, the worme a mother and ſiſter,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iob.</hi> 17.16.</note> when man goeth downe to the bowels of the pitte, and reſt muſt be in the duſt. <hi>It ſtirreth vp</hi> a man to good, to almes, to repentance, to diſpoſing of his houſe, as appeareth in <hi>Hezekiah</hi> when he had receaued the meſſage of death, hee turned his face to the wall,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>If.</hi> 38.14.</note> prayed and mourned as a Doue. <hi>Now</hi> he ſettleth himſelfe by a liuely faith the foundation of ſaluation, a ſearch and confeſſion of his former ſinnes, in a broken and contrite heart,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſ.</hi>
51.17.</note> by remiſſion of iniuries, ſubmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting himſelfe to Gods good pleaſure, vnlading himſelfe of ill gotten goods, running to obtaine.
<hi>Howſoeuer</hi> man hath thought of himſelfe before he be ſummoned to dye, and haue bragged with proud <hi>Phaeton</hi> in the Poet, that
<hi>Apollo</hi> were his father; yet now he muſt call to minde, that
<hi>Cli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mene</hi> was his mother: hee ſeeth that his ſtrength is not of
<hi>braſſe,</hi> his matter is not of gold, ſiluer, pretious ſtones, but earth: <hi>that</hi> life and death are in the hands of God, and haue their date and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiny by him: <hi>that</hi> we are caryed away as Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants in a ſhippe, whither we ſtand or ſit, watch or ſleepe, <hi>Senſim ſine ſenſu <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>neſcimus,</hi> olde age ſtealeth on, that hee that p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>ſeth himſelfe a long life, doth as he that looketh through a perſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectiue, conceaue thoſe things great which are
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:15638:15"/>very ſmall; <hi>that Death</hi> is a commanding Tyrant and will haue nodenyall. Hence is it called <hi>Duſt,</hi> If I haue rewarded euill to him that was at peace with me, let the enemy lay mine honour in the duſt: A <hi>brooke:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſ.</hi>
7.5.110.7. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 8 <hi>l.</hi> 3. <hi>Iob.</hi> 3.13. 1.
<hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.2. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.8. <hi>Ioſ.</hi> 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>4.</note> he ſhall drinke of the brooke in the way: The graue, my life draweth nigh vnto the graue: <hi>A ſleepe,</hi> A comming, as a <hi>theef</hi> in the night: A time of <hi>departure:</hi> the way <hi>of all the earth:</hi> Of
<hi>Abell</hi> whoſe ſacrifice God accepted, as of <hi>Cain,</hi> whoſe ſacrifice God deſpiſed: of <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> the Father of the faithfull, as well as of the children of vnbeliefe: of <hi>Izhac</hi> the ſonne of the free woman, as of <hi>Iſmael</hi> the ſonne of the bond woman: of
<hi>Iacob</hi> whom God loued, as of <hi>Eſau</hi> whom he hated: of
<hi>chaſt Ioſeph</hi> as of inceſtuous <hi>Ammon:</hi> of <hi>meeke Moyſes</hi> as rayling <hi>Rabſhekah:</hi> of <hi>zealous Phinees</hi> as the luke-warme Miniſter of the Church of <hi>Laodicea:</hi> of <hi>Dauid</hi> a man according to Gods owne heart, as <hi>Saul</hi> from whom God tooke his ſpirit: of <hi>Salomon</hi> the wiſe, as <hi>Nabal</hi> the foole: of tender hearted <hi>Ioſiah,</hi> as hard hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>Pharaoh:</hi> the humble
<hi>Publican,</hi> as the proud <hi>Phariſee:</hi> poore <hi>Lazarus</hi> to be carryed into <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hams</hi> boſome, as the rich glutton to be carryed into hell: <hi>Iohn</hi> the beloued Diſciple, as <hi>Iudas</hi> the traitor:
<hi>Simon Peter</hi> the Apoſtle, as <hi>Simon Magus</hi> the Sorcerer:
<hi>The death of Chriſt</hi> hath freed from the ſecond death, but not the firſt: He hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered the vſe of the firſt death, but not taken it away: it was ordained as a puniſhment, but he hath made it a paſſage into Heauen: and as by
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:15638:16"/>life man commeth to bondage, ſo by death his freedome is wrought, <hi>yet dye he muſt firſt;</hi> be he Natures
<hi>Paragon,</hi> he is but a lump of fleſh, and <hi>ſtraight after Birth is due the fatall Beere.</hi> Death is the <hi>Emperour</hi> of graues, common Inne, the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, tribute, Conquerour, receptacle of all: and as the Sunne where it ſhineth melteth the hardeſt ice, ſo where this Centurion com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands there muſt be obedience. <hi>This</hi> place ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie ſtriketh with a bloody dart, the wretched Caitiffe and the King alike: It ſends out a
<hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsion,</hi> as that voyce to <hi>Abraham, Exi de terra tua,</hi> Goe out of thy Country wherein thou wert bred and borne: come forth ye ſoules from thoſe bodyes, and though there be but one manner of comming into the world, yet are there many thouſand wayes of going out of the world. <hi>Wee are full of holes and breaches,</hi> One dyeth young, another in a good age, ſome when their breaſts are full of milke:<note place="margin">Eriyere vita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nemo non homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni petect. At nemo mortem, mille ad hanc patent aditus Se<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. trag.
<hi>3.</hi> Ac. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> Waite we muſt for our change, and patiently expect the execution of that De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree, which is ſo various and manifold, that no one mans tongue can poſſibly deſcribe it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Abell</hi> was ſlaine by his brother, <hi>Abimelechs</hi> brains beaten out by a woman, throwing a peece of a milſtone from a wall:
<hi>Agag</hi> washewed in peeces: <hi>Iſay</hi> cut a ſunder with a woodden ſawe:<note place="margin">Epipha de vitis Prophetarum.</note> 
                  <hi>Amos</hi> ſlaine with a doore barre: the Infants of <hi>Bethlehem</hi> were ſlaine in their Cradles, <hi>Eglon</hi> in his Parlour, <hi>Saul</hi> in the field,
<hi>Isboſheth</hi> in his bed, <hi>Sennacherib</hi> in the Temple,
<hi>Ioab</hi> at the very Altar: <hi>Beares</hi> ſlew
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:15638:16"/>the boyes that mocked <hi>Elizeus,</hi> wormes <hi>Herod,</hi> Lyons <hi>Daniels</hi> accuſers, Dogges <hi>Euripides. Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremity of ioy</hi> hath killed ſome, as <hi>Zeuxes, Diago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras, Rhodius, Sophocles:</hi> Sorrowe others, as old <hi>Eli, Homer, Vrbain</hi> the third. Fier deſtroyeth ſome, as the <hi>Sodomits, Nadab</hi> and <hi>Abihu, Zimri, Perillus.</hi> Water others, as <hi>M. Marcellus, Lauren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius Laurentinianus</hi> that great Phiſitian. Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quakes, <hi>Chore, Dathan, Abiron, M. Curtius. Hunger</hi> deſtroyed <hi>Cleanthes</hi> the Philoſopher. Thirſt, <hi>Tha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les Mileſius.</hi> Watching, <hi>M. Attilius Regulus.</hi> The fall of an houſe <hi>Athenaeus. Philippe</hi> a young French King called <hi>Groſſus,</hi> fell from his horſe dead:
<hi>Ieza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bell</hi> being caſt out of a windowe dyed:<note place="margin">Fulgo li. <hi>9</hi> c. <hi>1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Anacreon</hi> the Poet was choaked with the kernel of a raiſin: <hi>Valentinian</hi> the Emperour came to his end by ſtrayning himſelfe with crying too loud:<note place="margin">Pli. nat. li. <hi>7.7.</hi> Hier. op. <hi>9</hi> to. <hi>9</hi> Fulgo vbi ſupra Guido. Ful. ib. Pli. vt ſupra. Florus. lib. <hi>3.</hi> c. a <hi>3.</hi> Suides. Polyd. Virgil. hiſt Ang.</note> the <hi>yolke</hi> of an egge ſtifled
<hi>Saufeius:</hi> a fiſh bone <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quinius Priſcus:</hi> a peare
<hi>Druſus Pompeius:</hi> an haire in his milke <hi>Fabius</hi> the Senatour: a ſmoake <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullus</hi> the Orator: the hot Sunne
<hi>Chriſoſtome:</hi> a crumme of bread, <hi>Goodwin</hi> Earle of Kent. A
<hi>Pluriſie</hi> killed <hi>Charles</hi> the Great, a Diſſenterye,
<hi>Anaſtaſius</hi> the ſecond, the Cholicke <hi>Antiochus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iulius Ceſar</hi> diſputing the night before of the good of ſuddaine death, was the next day by <hi>Brutus</hi> and <hi>Caſsius</hi> ſlaine ſuddainely in the Senate: <hi>Iohannes Matheſius</hi> hauing preached of the rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of the Widdowe of <hi>Naimes</hi> ſonne, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
3. houres dyed: <hi>Luther</hi> hauing ſate at ſupper, and diſcourſed diuinely of the ioyes of Heauen,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:15638:17"/>about midnight after he ſlept in the Lord:
<hi>Iouian</hi> an Emperour was found dead in his bed: <hi>Pope Adrian</hi> the fourth was choaked with a flye:<note place="margin">Soz. hiſt Eccl.
<hi>6.6.</hi> crimoneſis</note> can we forget that dolefull DOLEFVLL EVENSONG of that Popiſh aſſembly in the Blacke-Fryers, mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerably miſled to heare a Ieſuite?<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Oct.</hi> 25.1623</note> 90. or 100. whereof periſhed while they heard <hi>Antichriſt</hi> exalted: I dare not be ſo vncharitable as from their <hi>temporall</hi> deſtruction to collect their eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall confuſion: <hi>But</hi> by theſe we may ſee no place is priuiledged from the arreſt of death. Some we ſee come to their graues by
<hi>Apoplexies,</hi> Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thargies, dead Palſies, ſome by ſuddaine blowes, ſome as a waſted candle, goe out naturally. How many doth that violent FEVER nowe ſweep away in our Cittie, and in the moſt parts of the Kingdome? an argument of Gods anger againſt vs, as he threatned the diſobedient children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dc.</hi> 28.15.22.</note> that if they would not hearken to his voyce to obſerue to doe all his Commandements and Statutes (the SINNE of ENGLAND) he would ſmite them with a FEVER, and with an inflam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, and with an extreame BVRNING. Our
<hi>Neighbours</hi> viſitation ſheweth vs <hi>Belſhazzars</hi> em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleme vpon our doors and walles, that our dayes are counted,<note place="margin">Vita cito auolat nec poteſt reti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neri mors quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tidie ingruit nec poteſt reſiſti.</note> that our life flyeth away daily and cannot be retained, and death is continually ready to ruſh vpon vs and cannot be reſiſted, but as wee haue had a time to be borne, ſo <hi>a time to DIE.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Let the <hi>Egiptians</hi> call man a reuerend and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:15638:17"/>creature, <hi>Mercury</hi> a great myracle,
<hi>Pytha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goras</hi> the meaſure of all things, <hi>Plato</hi> the wonder of wonders, <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> a politique creature, framed for ſociety,
<hi>Syneſius</hi> the Horizon of corporeall and incorporeall things,
<hi>Tully</hi> a diuine creature full of reaſon and iudgement,
<hi>Plinie</hi> the worlds Epitome, and Natures darling, yet he is mortall, and muſt yeeld to this heauy colde enemie, which ſneapeth the braueſt bloſſomes, and maketh them fade anon which ere while flouriſhed: the longeſt liuer dyes, and DEAD, the lowlieſt creature as the lothſome carion lyes. <hi>This is</hi> it that daunteth all earthly things, They were borne to dye: If they had a <hi>beginning,</hi> they muſt haue an end.
<hi>Death</hi> is impartiall, cutting off good and bad, It ſelfe knowne to all, the houre of it vnknowne to any: <hi>Nothing can reſiſt it,</hi> No Peeres, Princes, mortall wight; No Townes, Realmes, Cities, Towers:
<hi>All</hi> muſt runne this courſe, and whatſoeuer liues tis ſure to dye: Nothing vnder the Sunne is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortall: <hi>Death</hi> may claime his right vpon birth, God permits it, All haue their times dated in his booke of all diſpoſing prouidence: when the houre comes let none aske whence or why? All ſhould prepare for it: The goodlieſt <hi>Cities</hi> haue beene equalled with the ground, ſtatelieſt build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings leuelled with the earth, greateſt Empires brought to nothing: <hi>Kings</hi> haue beene bound in chaines, Nobles in fetters of iron. <hi>Wee</hi> waxe olde as a garment, dwell in houſes of clay, our breath goeth away, and we all periſh: <hi>Mathuſelah</hi> with his yeares, <hi>Samſon</hi> with his ſtrength, <hi>Abſolon</hi> with
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:15638:18"/>his beauty, <hi>Salomon</hi> with his wiſdome, they had a time of birth, and a time of buriall. Young men haue death at their <hi>backes,</hi> and olde men before their <hi>eyes;</hi> yet fewe deſire to looke vpon it, nay they cannot endure to heare, that as they haue had a time to be borne <hi>ſo a time to dye.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">VSE </seg>1</label> Which may ſeeke to
<hi>reproue</hi> many, who neuer ſeriouſly thinke vpon their mortality, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore are dead and buried in pleaſures while they liue, holding Repentance but an houres worke, Faith fancie, Religion a lip-labour, of whom wee may ſay as <hi>Martha</hi> of <hi>Lazarus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn</hi> 11.39.</note> He ſtinketh: <hi>Would</hi> we thinke vpon our end, we would not ſo offend, <hi>but</hi> the forgetfulneſſe of this, cauſeth <hi>wiſdome</hi> to be tainted with craft, Iuſtice with corruption, Faith with diſſimulation, Godlineſſe with hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie, Friendſhip with hope of gaine, Lending with vſurie: Wee liue in a quarrelling age, the moſt making ill vſe of Gods mercies, not endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring any correction. Wee haue enioyed a long time of <hi>peace,</hi> plenty, &amp; aboue all, the free paſſage of the Goſpell, yet our owne conſciences doe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe vs, that we haue neither worthily eſteemed, nor ſufficiently expreſſed the ſweet comfort of the Goſpell reuealed vnto vs; <hi>but</hi> workes be chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged into words, walking in goodneſſe into talk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of God, hands into tongues, hearts into cares: to cure ſuperſtition wee neglect true deuotion. <hi>Some</hi> haue
<hi>Iſraelitiſh</hi> ſtomacks, and loath Manna the bread of heauen; others <hi>Athenian</hi> cares itch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing after new Teachers and new Doctrines: Men
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:15638:18"/>rather ſeeke for profound knowledge, then for faith that worketh by loue: <hi>Preach</hi> we death and iudgement? men ſay (bleſſing themſelues in their hearts) we ſhall haue peace though we walke in the imaginations of our hearts,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Deu.</hi>
29.19.</note> to adde drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to thirſt. Hence</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Heu viuunt homines tanquam mors nulla ſequatur</l>
                  <l>Et velut infernus fabula vana foret.</l>
               </q>
               <p>Many liue as if they ſhould neuer dye, and as if <hi>hell</hi> were but a gulle and fable, But the <hi>Lord</hi> will not ſpare ſuch, his anger and iealouſie ſhall ſmoake againſt them, they ſhall haue ſickeneſſes and wounds, and the Lord will be vnto them as a moth &amp; as rottenneſſe.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 5.12.</note> 
                  <hi>Better a liuing Dogge then a dead Lyon,</hi> ſo long as we liue wee may repent, but after death <hi>Iudgement,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.</note> ordinary arguments; and the vſe of them hath taken away the force of them, but none ſo neceſſary. Is a man perſwaded that theſe are nigh? It will eaſily diſpatch, that which no Law, Prince, priſon, Parents or pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment could doe: they that before could take no counſaile, now giue good coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaile. <hi>Nothing ſo teacheth as the remembrance of death,</hi> as not onely appeares in <hi>Ezekias</hi> his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uout meditations, put vpon a perpetuall record by the holy Ghoſt, when he had but a tallie of dayes left him, but in <hi>Baltaſhazar</hi> who ſeeing the number of his dayes and that he was found too light, began to quake &amp; learne wiſdome: Deaths remembrance brings horror: <hi>O death</hi> how bitter is the remembrance of thee, to a man that liueth
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:15638:19"/>at reſt in his poſſeſſions:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ecc.</hi> 41.1.</note>: It comes with trouppes of ſorrowes,<note place="margin">Dr. Haywatd in his <hi>Sanct:</hi> of a troubled Soule.</note> 
                  <hi>the head ſhooting,</hi> the backe aking, the heart panting, the throat ratling, the tongue faltring, the breath ſhortening, the fleſh trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling, the veines beating, the heart ſtrings crac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, the eyes waxing dimme, the noſe ſharpe, the browes hard, the cheekes cold and wanne, the lippes pale, the hands numme, the ioynts ſtiffe, the whole body being in a cold-ſweat, the ſtrength fainting, the life vaniſhing, the ſtanders<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> by like fleſh flyes crying or crauing, offering to moleſt the dying body. <hi>Death</hi> ſeparates the ſoule, deuideth friends, ſpoiles a man of worldly goods though he heapes vpſiluer as the duſt, and prepare rayme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t as clay.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iob.</hi> 27.16.</note> 
                  <hi>Be not puffed</hi> vp with proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perity, you knowe not what a day may bring forth, the rankeſt corne is ſooneſt layde: I ſee that all things come to an end: <hi>This</hi> we muſt teach as <hi>Dauid</hi> did,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſ.</hi> 119.96.</note> and that ſurely men of lowe degree are vanitye,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pl.</hi> 62.9.</note> and men of high degree are a lye to belayd in the balances, they are altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther lighter then vanity.<note place="margin">Tot quotidie occidimus quot ad mortem ire tace<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes videmus Gr. lib. <hi>33.</hi> epi. ad Venan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium. Ac. <hi>20.26.</hi>
                  </note> In this <hi>point</hi> wee muſt not be ſilent, ſo many we kill as we ſuffer to runne on to death without warning. St. <hi>Paul</hi> would keepe nothing backe from the Epheſians, and ſhunned not to declare vnto them all the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaile of God, becauſe he would be pure from the blood of all men. I haue heard that <hi>Newes</hi> came to a certaine Towne, that AN ENEMIE was approaching, <hi>yet he came not:</hi> herevpon a <hi>Lawe</hi> was made, that none ſhould bring ſuch rumours
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:15638:19"/>of warres and newes of an Enemie: <hi>Not long after</hi> the enemie came, beſieged, aſſaulted, ruinated the Towne, and thence grew a Prouerbe, THAT PLACE WAS DESTROIED BY SILENCE: Let vs lift vp our <hi>voyces</hi> as Trumpetes herein, and though men be as gods vpon earth, Let vs preach <hi>Mans mortality,</hi> and preſſe for fruites worthy a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendment of life, that there may be comfort in death. Hath <hi>God</hi> made thee a little world, and aboue all earthly creatures, giuen to thee an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortall ſoule, <hi>foreſeing</hi> things to come, <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membring</hi> things paſt, <hi>iudging</hi> of things preſent, <hi>bearing</hi> the image of God? made thee erect to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the Heauens, promiſed a reſurrection of thy body and life euerlaſting, and wilt thou abuſe the goodneſſe of God which leadeth to repentance? If he be prouoked, he is a conſuming fire: He which in health hath beene diligent to <hi>feare God</hi> and to doe good, ſhall feele in ſickeneſſe an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable comfort, which he will not miſſe for all the whole world, and a mighty boldeneſſe to ſpeake vnto God, <hi>But</hi> he which whiles the world proſpered with him neuer thought vppon God, nor regarded his word, when the viſitation of the Lord is vpon him, when his ſoule is ready to bee taken from him, his heart being hardned in ſin, &amp; he hauing made no preparatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for DEAEH; terrour ſhal take hold on him as waters; a tempeſt ſhall ſteale him away in the night; a ſtorme ſhall hurle him out of his place, men ſhall clappe their hands at him, &amp; ſhall hiſſe him out of his place:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iob.</hi> 27.22.23</note>
               </p>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:15638:20"/>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">VSE </seg>2</label> An <hi>Inſtruction</hi> for vs to haue our accounts in a readineſſe, that whenſoeuer the Lord ſhall call vs by his <hi>Bayliefe Death,</hi> he may find vs prepared; that we may keepe a Kalender, and Ephemerides of our time, how it paſſeth away; that as our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies ſtoop downwards by yeares and infirmities, ſo our ſoules ſoare vpward; that we may haue our Loyns girt &amp; our Lamps burning. While we are in the world, we are in a Sea of troubles; we ſaile as Pilgrimes, toſſed by the tempeſts of aduerſity, oppreſſed by three Pyrates; the Fleſh, World, Deuill: Yet by the Barke of a liuely Faith, this Marriner <hi>Death</hi> may tranſport vs from <hi>Aegipt</hi> to <hi>Canaan.</hi> For howſoeuer death (to the Repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate) be the Curſe of God, Suburbes of Hell, Pyrate of life, the Diuels Serieant to arreſt and carry them without bayle to a Priſon of vtter darkneſſe; his Cart to bring them to execution, from which there can be no repriuement: <hi>Yet</hi> to the <hi>Godly</hi> it is not
<hi>exitus,</hi> but <hi>tranſitus:</hi> a depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture but a paſſage:<note place="margin">Cyp. ſc. de mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal.</note> 
                  <hi>Fratres mortui non ſunt amiſsi ſed praemiſsi.</hi> Our dead Friends are not loſt, they are but ſent before. <hi>Profectio eſt quam putas mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem:</hi> that thou thinkeſt death,<note place="margin">Au. ep. <hi>6.</hi>
                  </note> is but a iourney to them,<note place="margin">Tert. de Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tientia.</note> to the Land of the liuing; The key to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>locke from miſery, and ſend abroade to liberty: A Bridge to paſſe from a vale of teares, to a pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe of joyes. Like the
<hi>Brazen Serpent,</hi> ſo farre from hurting true <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> that it healeth them. <hi>The</hi> beginning of joy, firſt fruites of pleaſure, Prince of delight, and a Maſſenger of glad ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings:
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:15638:20"/>A paſſage from labour to reſt: Bleſſed are the dead which dye in the Lord,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Reu.</hi>
14.13</note> that they may reſt from their laboures: From vileneſſe to glory; <hi>Lazarus</hi> was carryed by the Angels into <hi>Abrahams</hi> boſome: <hi>From</hi> feare to ſecurity, The wicked is driuen away in their wickedneſſe,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luk.</hi> 14.22.</note> but the righteous hath ioy in his death:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pr.</hi> 14.32.</note>
                  <hi>From</hi> trouble to peace, as olde <hi>Tobit</hi> prayed, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maund my ſpirit to be taken from me,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Tob.</hi> 3.6.</note> that I may be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolued, that I may be deliuered out of this di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe, and goe into the euerlaſting place: <hi>From</hi> an vncertain commorancie to a ſetled habitario<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, an eternall houſe in the Heauens:<note place="margin">2.
<hi>Co.</hi> 5.1.</note> 
                  <hi>From</hi> capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uity to liberty; therefore St.
<hi>Paul</hi> wiſhed: O wretched man that I am,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ro.</hi> 7.24.</note> who ſhall deliuer mee from the body of death? <hi>From</hi> vanitie to glory, which made the ſame Apoſtle ſo confident; To me to liue is Chriſt, and to dye is gaine.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ph.</hi> 1.21.</note> To the <hi>Godly</hi> it is a coaſt for them baniſhed out of this world, a landing at the Hauen; a laying downe of a heauy burthen of the body, the conſumption of all diſeaſes, the eſcaping of all perills, breaking of all Bonds, returne to our owne home.<note place="margin">Eſt vitae vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus maxima poſſe mori. Mat.
<hi>24.42.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>THIS</hi> we ſhould often thinke vpon, becauſe the greateſt worke we haue to doe, is to dye well: And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Chriſt commaundeth; watch, for yee know not what houre your Lord will come: what I ſay vnto you, I ſay vnto you all, watch:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mar.</hi>
13.37.</note> Like vnto men that waite for their Lord, when he will returne from the wedding;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luk.</hi> 12.36.</note> that when he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth and knocketh, yee may open to him imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatly.
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:15638:21"/>It is too late to recall the Bargaine, the Bond being ſealed; to defend the Walles, when the Citty is ouercome; to ſound a retraite, when the Battaile is fought; to ſend for a
<hi>Phyſitian,</hi> when the ſicke party is dead: When time is paſt, it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be recalled. Therefore ſaith the <hi>wiſe</hi> man, whatſoeuer thy hand findeth to doe, doe it with thy might; for there is no worke, nor deuiſe, nor knowledge,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ecl.</hi> 9.10.</note> nor wiſedome in the Graue whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thou goeſt.<note place="margin">Guil. paris. p
<hi>5.</hi> de. vitijs tr. de accidia. Gr. Ho. <hi>13.</hi> in Eua. Bonau. Sanchez in Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſ.</note> Hereafter is no time of work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, but rewarding:
<hi>Hereafter Ariſtotles</hi> arguments will not ſerue to excuſe or defend, but rather to accuſe. If we feare death before it come, we ſhall conquer it: There is no <hi>deliberating</hi> hereafter: There ſhall be no profit of the knowledge of Diuine or Humane things hereafter, vnles wee vſe it well in this life. God hath giuen a Talent to exerciſe euery man; ſome worke for euery one againſt his comming into the world: Skill and knowledge is long and difficult, life is ſhort and ſickly; we ſhould as oportunity ſerueth, performe our duty towards our God,<note place="margin">Ars longa, vita breuis. Hipocr.</note> towards our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boures, towards our ſelues. The time of <hi>Working</hi> ceaſeth in the graue: None can be benifited by our workes, wiſedome, skill, counſell, when we are dead: We cannot praiſe God nor glorifie him in the <hi>graue. Now</hi> is the time of vſing and beſtowing thoſe gifts that God hath giuen for his glory in this life; And this time ſaith <hi>Iob</hi> is ſwif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then a Poſte, paſſeth away as the ſwift Ship; and as the <hi>Eagle</hi> haſteth to her pray: Nothing ſo
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:15638:21"/>ſwift in the <hi>Land, Sea, Ayre;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iob.</hi> 9.26.</note> as a ſhadow ſo paſſeth our time; or as when an <hi>Arrowe</hi> is ſhot at a Mark, it parteth the ayre, which immediatly commeth together againe;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Wiſ.</hi>
5.9.12.13</note> ſo that a man cannot knowe where it went through. Euen ſo we in like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner as ſoon as we are born, begin to draw to our end. Our Bodyes too and froe; we ſhall not bee that to morrow which we are to day.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Noſtra quoque ipſorum ſemperequie<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſine vlla</l>

                  <l>Corpora vertuntur,<note place="margin">Ou. Metam. l.
<hi>1.</hi>
                     </note> nec quod fuimuſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſumuſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan>
                  </l>
                  <l>Cras erimus.</l>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Let vs not</hi> till the day of death delay our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſion. when <hi>ſickneſſe</hi> ſummoneth and bindeth vpon the Alter, for the ſacrificing of the Soule; wicked actions, words, thoughts, will appeare armed with Gods anger, and with the Curſes of of the Law heaped together, agrauated to the vttermoſt, giuing the Conſcience many a colde pull, and lying vpon the heart as heauie as Lead: <hi>The</hi> Conſcience will accuſe, the Memory giue bitter euidence, Reaſon will ſit as Iudge, Feare ſhall ſtand as executioner. <hi>Let vs now</hi> therefore get a good life, that it may be an vſher to a good death. <hi>Let</hi> vs drawe good out of euill, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide for immortallity in the time of mortallity. <hi>Let vs</hi> dye willingly, ſeeing we muſt dye neceſſari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, we ſhall liue eternally. <hi>Let not</hi> the worlds pleaſures detaine vs, but rather draw our affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s to thoſe things which are aboue; knowing that
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:15638:22"/>if there be ſuch delight in any thing of this mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall life,<note place="margin">Giſelbertus in li. Altere. c.
<hi>3.</hi> Hic vel acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pienus vel amit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timus vitam eternam. Cyp.</note> which conſiſts in the preſence of the Soule in a corruptible body; what immortall pleaſure ſhall there be, when the preſence of the Godhead ſhall fill the reaſonable Soule? <hi>Now</hi> is the time to get this aſſurance; here we may win or loſe it:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gal.</hi>
6.7.</note> Let vs not be weary in well doing: As we ſowe, ſo we ſhall reape.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Quod ſibiquiſque ſerit, praeſentis tempore vitae</l>
                  <l>Hoc ſibi meſsis erit, cum dicitur Ite, venite.</l>
               </q>
               <p>If we would not heare in the great <hi>Haruest</hi> of the laſt iudgement that terrible voyce, which ſhall be vſed to them on the left hand, Depart from me ye curſed into euerlaſting fire prepared for the Deuill and his Angels,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.41.</note> Let vs
<hi>Nowe</hi> heare that ſweete voyce calling to repentance, Come ye Bleſſed children of my Father: Learne of me for I am meeke and lowely, and ye ſhall finde reſt vnto your ſoules.<note place="margin">Mat.
<hi>11.29.</hi> Qualem te inuenerit Deus cum vocat, tale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pariter iudicat. Cyp. lib. <hi>4.</hi> de morte.</note> As the day of <hi>Death</hi> findeth vs, ſo ſhall the laſt day iudge vs. <hi>Let</hi> vs ſtand vppon our watch, and waite for it all the dayes of our appointed time. <hi>Let</hi> vs learne nowe to be acquainted with God in his world. <hi>Let</hi> vs conſecrate to him the Temples of our bodyes, and Altars of our ſoules, who created them of nothing, redeemed them when they were worſe then nothing, and hath appointed manſions for them with himſelfe in glory. <hi>Let</hi> vs get AGOOD NAME which will be better then <hi>all ointments</hi> and <hi>treaſures:</hi> They may be bought for mony, but this is the gift of God not to be purchaſed with
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:15638:22"/>baſe mettall. <hi>They</hi> are corruptible, this is euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting. <hi>They</hi> heaue a man in death, and betake them to a new Maſter, but the praiſe of the IVST man remaineth ſtill his owne. It taryeth behind him on earth, and goeth with him to heauen, and will crowne him with glory at the laſt day. <hi>Let</hi> vs eſteeme the day of Death better then our Birth-day. That was an entrance into miſery, this will giue vs a paſſe for felicity. <hi>Let</hi> vs now re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member our Creatour. <hi>Let</hi> vs take time while it is offered vnto vs to prepare for Heauen, <hi>Time</hi> will away. <hi>Let</hi> vt not neglect our tide, but bee wiſe in paſſing the time of our pilgrimage here on earth. <hi>All muſt dye:</hi> our ſtroke will come, how ſoone and ſuddainely, when or where, we knowe not. We ſhould <hi>impart</hi> this in our memory, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially ſeeing the <hi>Lord</hi> ſtrikes thoſe who were neare vnto vs, and we may complaine, that THE RIGHTEOVS PERISHE: As <hi>they</hi> had <hi>A time to be Borne ſo a time to Die.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>My Texte</hi> is occaſioned to me vpon the taking away of a <hi>Worthy flower</hi> of our Pariſh <hi>Sir Willam Byrde,</hi> a
<hi>Father</hi> of the lawe, and a <hi>Iuſt</hi> and merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<hi>Patron</hi> of Widdowes and Orphanes, a meeke <hi>Moſes,</hi> an vpright
<hi>Samuell,</hi> a zealous <hi>Iob,</hi> fearing <hi>God,</hi> eſchewing euill, a man of <hi>courage, dealing true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, hating couetouſneſſe:</hi> I confeſſe that his ſoule being taken into the ſociety of heauenly Saints, neither careth for, nor ſeekeeth our praiſes, <hi>Yet let not the godly be forgotten:</hi> though dead we may commend them. It is
<hi>lawfull</hi> in it ſelfe, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:15638:23"/>for the liuing for <hi>imitation:</hi> Therefore <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> commended <hi>Ionathan</hi> for his loue:<note place="margin">2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 1.26. 2. <hi>Ch.</hi> 35.23.</note> the holy
<hi>Ghoſt</hi> King <hi>Ioſiah</hi> for his integrity: St. <hi>Paul</hi> in that Epiſtle to the Hebrewes the <hi>Patriarches</hi> and Prophets:
<hi>Chriſt</hi> commanded that whereſoeuer the <hi>Goſpell</hi> ſhould be preached,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Math.</hi> 26.18.</note> mention ſhould be made of that good worke of the woman: we may commend a <hi>Sayler</hi> when hee arriues at the hauen, and a <hi>Souldier</hi> when he hath conquered.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Vniuerſity</hi> bred him, <hi>Antient Oxford,</hi> a graue mother of many worthies in Iſrael,<note place="margin">All ſoules Colledge.</note> where in he tooke his degrees, <hi>ex merito</hi> not <hi>ex mera gra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tia.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In that worthy and flouriſhing Society where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he liued, he was no <hi>factious</hi> Incendiary <hi>(And O let peace as plenty euer be within thoſe walles)</hi> For howſoeuer <hi>Bee</hi>-keepers iudge that
<hi>ſwarme</hi> to bee moſt fruitfull in making honey,<note place="margin">Aral. <hi>9.</hi> de hiſt. Animal. c. <hi>40.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <hi>apud quod ſtrepitus ſufurrus, frequenſque tumultus plurimorum eſt,</hi> which buzzeth moſt and maketh the greateſt tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mult; yet in a
<hi>ciuill</hi> Hiue they are iudged to make the moſt <hi>hony</hi> who are moſt peaceable, for <hi>Buſie bodyes worke nothing at all</hi> but
<hi>canuaſes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He was no <hi>Muſhrum</hi> to riſe vp in a moment, like thoſe Giants <hi>ſimul ſati &amp; editi,</hi> ſowne and growne in an inſtant, ſuppoſing themſelues <hi>of ſufficiencie enough becauſe they can giue enough for a preferment,</hi> their <hi>paſsions</hi> being guided by pride and follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by <hi>iniuſtice,</hi> and when greateſt are but as a <hi>puddle</hi> vpon which the Sunne ſhineth. <hi>He roſe</hi> to his degrees of <hi>dignity</hi> by <hi>iuſt</hi> and <hi>faire</hi> degrees,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:15638:23"/>
                  <hi>honoring</hi> the places he had with his worth as they him with their greatneſſe: For as <hi>Tully</hi> tolde
<hi>Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar</hi> to ſet the vnworthy in high <hi>places</hi> is not ſo much to grace the perſons by place as to diſgrace the place by ſuch
<hi>perſons.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>He</hi> was fit for <hi>gouernement</hi> hauing a ſounde
<hi>head</hi> and ſanctifyed <hi>heart,</hi> carefull to auoyde the worlds ſcandals, <hi>diligent</hi> in comming with his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily to the Church,
<hi>reuerendly</hi> attentiue in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the word, religiouſly
<hi>humbled</hi> in receauing the Sacrament. How <hi>cheerefully</hi> would he diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe as his table of what had bene deliuered in. Gods houſe?</p>
               <p>It hath often reioycedime to ſee the <hi>true loues Chriſtian knot</hi> a ſweet vnity &amp; <hi>harmony</hi> betwit him and his
<hi>joyall and vertuous Lady:</hi> &amp; where ſhould we finde loue &amp;
<hi>Concorde,</hi> if not twixt <hi>husband &amp; wife?</hi> They are <hi>one fleſh</hi> by originall <hi>creation,</hi> for the woman came of the man, &amp; by a <hi>Nuptiall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iunction,</hi> the woman is fleſh of the fleſh of man, &amp; ſtands on euen ground with the man, though drawing on the left ſide: <hi>No bitterneſſe</hi> ſhould be there, and therfore among the
<hi>Heathen,</hi> the galle of the <hi>ſacrifice</hi> that was ſlaine and offered at the wedding was throwne out at doores,<note place="margin">Plut. in praee. Coning.</note> ſignifying that the <hi>maryed folkes</hi> ſhould be either to other as <hi>Doues without galle.</hi> Husband and wife haue a
<hi>triple band</hi> of loue A <hi>naturall</hi> as neighbours, A
<hi>ſpirituall</hi> as fellowe members of the body of Chriſt, An holy and
<hi>honourable</hi> as one fleſh by mariage.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The</hi> loue of this learned man was great to
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:15638:24"/>
                  <hi>Gods word,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hier. de Nepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiano.</note> ſo that <hi>pectus ſuum Bibliothecam fecit Chriſti,</hi> he made his breaſt a library to Chriſt to be bound vp there: <hi>Hereby</hi> he learned to carry him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe ſo temperatly and fairely, knowing that the Hill of <hi>greatneſse</hi> howſouer it yeeld a delighfull proſpect, yet is ſubiect to <hi>lightning and thunder,</hi> remembring that he was to giue his account to him that is <hi>Iudex viuorum &amp; mortuorum,</hi> from whom there is no <hi>appeale:</hi> and
<hi>howſoeuer</hi> many op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunities of bribes, letters, and other
<hi>engines</hi> of corruptions were offered him ſome times, he kept his hands cleane, becauſe he had a <hi>pure heart. This made</hi> him reioyce in the the teſtimony of a <hi>Good conſcience,</hi> which as he profeſſed in his ſicke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe was as <hi>aqua vitae</hi> to cheere vp his drooping ſpirits: <hi>The Fathers</hi> call it the field of
<hi>bleſſedneſse,</hi> garden of <hi>delight,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Aug.</note> Ioy of <hi>Angels,</hi> houſe of the <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt,</hi> Paradiſe of the <hi>ſoule.</hi> It made <hi>Iob</hi> more happy in <hi>ſtercore,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iob.</hi> 27.6.</note> on the dunghill, then <hi>Adam</hi> was <hi>in memore,</hi> in the midſt of Paradiſe, <hi>That his heart reproched them not.</hi> It maketh a man though he had <hi>Giges</hi> ring to walke without the controlement of any eye, to walke vprightly.</p>
               <p>He was often deſired not to <hi>trouble</hi> himſelfe ſo much in his place of <hi>Iudicature,</hi> but to ſuffer <hi>Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogates</hi> to diſpatch buſineſſe for him, which hee ſeldome did, ſaying, I will do what I may poſſible by my ſelfe, <hi>I (and not they)</hi> muſt anſwer if wrong be done: <hi>And when I ſhall be vpon my death Bed, clamoures will trouble me if any be iniured.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>He</hi> laboured to make his <hi>Houſe</hi> a ſpectacle
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:15638:24"/>of deuout <hi>diſcipline</hi> to others,<note place="margin">Hier, de Nepo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiano. Domus eius erat magiſtra pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licae diſciplinae.</note> humbling himſelfe and his whole family before God, with <hi>Riligious praiers, often three times a day. A Method</hi> which he learned from holy <hi>King Dauid.</hi> Euening and morning, and at noone, will I pray and crye aloud, and he ſhall heare my voyce:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſ.</hi> 55.17.</note> Which the Fathers aſcribe to the Myſterie of the <hi>Paſsion, Reſurrection, aſcention</hi> of Chriſt:<note place="margin">Aug. Hier. Ruff Bed. Remig.</note> Three times a day the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> inioyned that the <hi>Lords Prayer</hi> ſhould be vſed:<note place="margin">Cle. <hi>7.</hi> Conſtit. <hi>25. Mr.</hi> hiſt. ſchol in Daniel. c. <hi>9.</hi>
                  </note> Three times a day the <hi>Iewes</hi> prayed, the third houre becauſe the Law was then giuen, the <hi>ſixt</hi> becauſe the Brazen Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent was then erected, the <hi>ninth</hi> becauſe then water came out of the Rocke. Three times a day the <hi>Church</hi> of the antient Chriſtians had praiers, becauſe at the <hi>third</hi> houre the holy Ghoſt was giuen; the <hi>ſixt</hi> Chriſt was crucified, the
<hi>ninth</hi> he was pierced through with a ſpeare:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dan.</hi> 6.9.</note> Three times a day <hi>Daniel</hi> kneeled vpon his knees, and prayd and gaue thankes before his God: Three times a day <hi>Prayers</hi> haue beene enioyned, <hi>either</hi> in honour of the holy, bleſſed, glorious three perſons of the Trinity: <hi>or</hi> becauſe we ſhould get the practiſe of the three Theological Vertues, Faith, Hope, Charity: <hi>or</hi> becauſe we ſhould haue a watch ouer three doors, the heart, mouth, action: <hi>or</hi> three <hi>Tempters,</hi> the luſt of the Fleſh, pride of the eyes, pride of life: <hi>or</hi> our three great <hi>Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies,</hi> the Fleſh, World, Deuill: <hi>or</hi> becauſe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing doth ſo adorne man in the three parts of his life, Childhood, Youth, Olde age.</p>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:15638:25"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>This</hi> learned and reuerend <hi>Iudge</hi> had the ſixe Properties required in a <hi>Iudge; Skill, Goodnes, Diligence,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Nuizanus ex Ioh. Pirrho in l. imperia. ff. de regul. iur. Barbatus. in Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit. Quoniam ſ. in alijs.</note> 
                  <hi>Eloquence, conſtancie, Prudence:</hi> Hee had <hi>ſalem ſcientiae &amp; conſcientiae,</hi> conſcience to ſeaſon his knowledge; without which the minde of a
<hi>Iudge</hi> is <hi>diabolicall and vnſanory.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hee</hi> was truely <hi>Miles Chriſtianus</hi> a Chriſtian Knight, in whom it is eſteemed no leſſe greatnes of heart to
<hi>reſiſt vice</hi> then to fight againſt enemies: the goodnes of a
<hi>Knight</hi> conſiſting not in Pompe and great magnificence,<note place="margin">Guenara.</note> but in the <hi>tranquillitie</hi> &amp;
<hi>innocencie</hi> of a good <hi>conſcience:</hi> For he that wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth in the wealth of <hi>Craeſus</hi> and <hi>ſleepeth</hi> not in the boſome &amp; quietneſſe of <hi>Abraham</hi> holdeth no more then if he were
<hi>Lord</hi> of a goodly veſſell re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleniſhed with corrupt and poiſoned <hi>liquor:</hi> To haue rich <hi>tapistrie,</hi> maſſie
<hi>plate,</hi> great <hi>horſes,</hi> and other preparations to ſportes and pleaſures, be things rather to get <hi>honourable names</hi> then to keep
<hi>Soules</hi> in ſafety.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>My wiſh</hi> is that as the trophees of <hi>Miltiades</hi> wold not ſuffer <hi>Themistocles</hi> to ſleep, til by the like acts, he had purchaſed to himſelfe the like glorious name:<note place="margin">Val. Max. l. <hi>8.</hi> c <hi>15.</hi> &amp; Plut.</note> ſo all of that hourable profeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Law, would looke into this glaſſe, &amp; make him a
<hi>Canon</hi> of their Ciuill &amp; Chriſtian imitation,<note place="margin">Vitam caeleſtem egit in terris. Hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. vita Pauli Eremitae.</note> following him as he followed Chriſt, in a <hi>heauenly courſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>If</hi> I ſhould ſpend many words more about him, I ſhould but ſtrike wounds into their mindes whom I deſire to comfort.
<hi>His hearty deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to God,</hi> tender compaſſion to pouerty, affa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:15638:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>kindneſſe to his friends,<note place="margin">In illo vno non vnum ſed plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res amiſſos re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quirimus. Amb. de exceſſu Satyr.</note> milde affection to his ſeruants, harmeleſſe behauiour and meaning to all, make vs complaine, that <hi>In</hi> his loſſe alone we haue not loſt him alone, but in him many a <hi>worthy</hi> one.
<hi>He liued like a Doue, dyed like a Lambe:</hi> when <hi>God</hi> ſtroke him abroad and ſummoned him to death by ſickeneſſe,<note place="margin">From Grauſende.</note> he was perſwaded to returne by water, where how ſweetly did he ſing <hi>Pſalmes?</hi> as knowing that a
<hi>Pſalme</hi> is <hi>mirth of the minde,</hi> tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>quility of the ſoule, an Ambaſſadour of peace, a ruler of the affections, a procurer of charity, reconciler of loue,<note place="margin">Baſ. homil. in Pſal.
<hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>neither</hi> is any ſo troubled in minde and diſturbed in <hi>thought,</hi> but if he takes the <hi>Pſalmes</hi> he may be ſtraight appeaſed.<note place="margin">Dyon. c. <hi>3.</hi> de diu. nom. p. <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>The Pſalter</hi> is a briefe of all the myſteries of the Bible: A <hi>Pſalme</hi> ſung with the intention of the heart maketh way for the ſoule to God:<note place="margin">Greg bom. <hi>1.</hi> in Ez. Innoc. <hi>3.</hi> proe. in Pſ. <hi>7.</hi> poenit. Hier. ep.
<hi>17.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Next to the Lords prayer,</hi> there cannot be better formes of prayer vſed then out of the Pſalmes: <hi>Ierome</hi> commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the Plough-men of <hi>Bethlehem</hi> for ſinging Pſalmes while they followed the Plough:<note place="margin">In Epitaph. Paulae. Conc. Nanne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſe cap. <hi>4.</hi>
                  </note> the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy <hi>Paula</hi> for ſinging the Pſalms,
<hi>A Counſaile</hi> inioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned that the ſeauen poenitentiall Pſalmes, which are the 6.32.38.51.102.130.143. ſhould be ſung by the Prieſt at the viſiting of the Sicke. <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his <hi>Apoſtles</hi> ſung a Hymne after the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament,<note place="margin">Mat. <hi>26.30.</hi> Paul. Burge. in Marc. <hi>14.</hi>
                  </note> the <hi>Iewes</hi> ſung ſeauen Pſalmes after the eating of the <hi>Paſchall</hi> Lambe,<note place="margin">Baro. Annal. p.
<hi>1.</hi> Hier.</note> from the 112. to the 119. and one of theſe it is probable <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſung:<note place="margin">Cantator Cyg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus funeris ipſe ſui Martialis.</note> and ſome thinke the 113. though others thinke it were the 21. He ſung as a <hi>Swan</hi> before
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:15638:26"/>his death:<note place="margin">Philo Iud. l. de ſupplicum vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutibus.</note> 
                  <hi>ſinging</hi> of Pſalmes was vſed by the <hi>pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitiue Chriſtians.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Vpon</hi> his returne to his houſe, he being lodged vpon his bed of ſickeneſſe in a burning feuer <hi>(the diſeaſe of the time which the right hand of the Lord re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moue from vs)</hi> how did he poſſeſſe his ſoule in <hi>pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience</hi> and a humble
<hi>ſubmiſsion</hi> to the hand of God, acknowledging Gods great mercies which he had receaued and found nowe continued, and herein gratiouſly that
<hi>God had chaſtiſed him,</hi> but without extraordinary ſenſible payne, and ſo had no <hi>heauier a burthen</hi> vppon him then hee coulde beare. He ſent for me being his poore Paſtour, but my occaſion of Attendance had called mee abroad: yet another <hi>Meſſenger</hi> of Gods word came to him: <hi>He welcomed</hi> him with all reſpect;
<hi>confeſſed</hi> his ſinnes, his ſorrowes, his faith, <hi>prayed</hi> earneſtly and feruently with <hi>ſighes</hi> and grones, and often cryed out, <hi>Lord IESVS be mercifull vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me, and receaue my ſoule,</hi> and ſo as he had <hi>a time to be borne</hi> ſo <hi>a time to dye:</hi> He ſlept in the Lord: <hi>Extremity</hi> of paines hath chaſed his ſoule out of his body, and I aſſure my ſelfe Angels haue car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed it into the boſome of <hi>Abraham.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Currum conſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendit, non eſt iam trepidare ne cadat. Bar. in tranſitu Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lachiae.</note> 
                  <hi>He is Now</hi> ſecure where he cannot fall: He is in the <hi>Quire of the Saints,</hi> his body is gone to earth, his ſoule to Chriſt: <hi>Happy he</hi> taken away not to ſee the conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance of ſinnes and conſequents of puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments:<note place="margin">Sanctorum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mixtus eſt cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris, corpus ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra ſuſcepit, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nima Chriſto reddita est. Foe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lix qui haec non vidit: foelix qui haec non audit. Nos miſeri at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tamen viuere volumus. Quem corpore non va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemus, recorda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione teneaemus: cum quo loqui non poſſumus, de co loqui non eſinamus. Hier. ad Helio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor. Epitaph. Nepotiani. Ecc.
<hi>39.2.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Wretched men</hi> that we are who deſire no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but life. <hi>His body</hi> wee cannot hold, yet let him not be forgotten in our mindes. <hi>We</hi> cannot
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:15638:26"/>ſpeake <hi>with</hi> him, Let vs often ſpeak <hi>of him,</hi> how he gaue his minde to the <hi>Lawe</hi> of the higheſt, ſought out the wiſdom of the Antient, was able to powre out wiſe Sentences, and therefore his <hi>Memoriall</hi> ſhall not depart away from vs: <hi>Bleſſed</hi> is he in his happy change from <hi>night to day,</hi> from <hi>darkeneſſe to light,</hi> from <hi>death to life,</hi> from <hi>ſorrowe to ſolace,</hi> from a <hi>factious world to a Countrye of peace, new Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem,</hi> where our God ſhall at the laſt day keepe his great Seſſions for eternall <hi>peace,</hi> conſcience being the
<hi>Clarke</hi> of that peace, an <hi>Angell</hi> the cryer of peace, the MESSIAS the Iudge of peace, <hi>Saints</hi> the Iury for peace,
<hi>Innocent</hi> the verdit of peace, <hi>Come ye Bleſſed of my Father</hi> the <hi>Oye</hi> of peace, <hi>Receaue the Kingdome</hi> the Sentence of peace. <hi>Let vs waite</hi> for the Redemptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the body, &amp; lift vp our heads after our <hi>Home aboue:</hi> Let vs labour to be found without ſpot and blameleſſe, <hi>Let vs learne to liue well, that we may dye well:</hi> Let vs la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment our loſſe of our worthies, but reioyce for their gaine: <hi>Let</hi> vs comfort our ſelues in hope of a <hi>ioyfull Reſurrection,</hi> through Ieſus Chriſt our Reſurrection and life,
<hi>To whom with the Father and the Holy Ghoſt, bee aſcribed all honour, and glory, nowe and euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more. Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
